Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, Spring 2014, 0.75 linear feet (1 full letter box, 1 half letter box; closed files in a third box shared with 2015-S-0068); 39 Gigabytes (60 digital video and text files)
  - Jodie Shapiro interviewed by Jessica Beliles, 2014 April 1; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Shapiro describes her childhood in a working class neighborhood and her early activist roots learned from her parents, while elaborating on their complicated relationship. She speaks about founding a women's resource center (which included a women's library) while she attended State University College of Buffalo. She also speaks extensively about how she met her partner and tells their entire love story. She also focuses on her travels cross-country and her subsequent discovery of various women's communities all across the U.S., as well as her involvement in a multitude of activist movements and groups in the Northampton area. In this interview, Shapiro explicitly outlines many of the struggles in her life as a lesbian.
    - Video interview of Jodie Shapiro
    - Transcript of interview of Jodie Shapiro (Box 2)
  - Susan Stinson interviewed by Kate Scrimshaw-Hall, 2014 March 14
    - Video interview of Susan Stinson
    - Transcript of interview of Susan Stinson (Box 3)
      Closed pending narrator edits, sections closed until 2044. No online access.
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, Fall 2014, 0.75 linear feet (1 letter document box, 1 half letter document box; additional closed materials in a half letter document box); 33.5 Gigabytes (69 digital video and text files)
  - Elizabeth Brook interviewed by Hana Sarfan, 2014 November 14; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    In this oral history, Lis Brook begins by describing her childhood, family, and early coming-out experience in New Jersey. The interview includes her activism in the antiwar movement, and more substantially, her work in the women's movement since the early 1970s. She describes harassment and corrective rape against lesbians in Northampton and the way that her community resisted these acts of violence. Brook's story details her efforts to create lesbian only space as well as the ways in which her attempts were challenged, and sometimes derailed. Lis describes her experience with butch/femme dynamics, the development of her women's only restaurant, and her future visions for new lesbian communities. The interview concludes with Brooks' reflections on her work as a therapist, her personal spirituality, and relationship with family during her adult life.
    Elizabeth Brook is a sixty-three year old lesbian from West Caldwell, New Jersey. She earned a Masters of Education in counseling psychology and has worked as a therapist focusing on women who struggle with trauma recovery and depression. Lis has been an active lesbian feminist advocate in the Pioneer Valley since she arrived in Northampton in 1973. She founded a women's restaurant, which served as an all-purpose women's center. Activist organizations she has participated in include a feminist theatre, a nonprofit that serves elderly lesbians, a feminist bookstore, and the Northampton pride march. Her primary feminist goal has been cultivating lesbian only spaces. She currently lives with her partner, Nancy, in Williamsburg, Massachusetts.
    This interview is available for research without restriction.
    - Transcript of interview of Elizabeth (Lis) Brook (Box 1)
  - Dawn M. Faucher interviewed by Nikila Krishnaveni Lakshmanan, 2014 November 7; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    Dawn Faucher (b. 1965) grew up in Hartford, Connecticut and graduated from Mt. Holyoke College with a major in Psychology and a minor in Spanish in May 1987. At age twenty-nine, Faucher became President of the Berkshire County Chapter of the Junior League, and the youngest President of a Chapter of the Junior League in the history of the Junior Leagues. After losing custody of her two children to her abusive husband, Faucher participated in a project called the Battered Mother's Testimony Project, in which she testified about her experience of domestic violence and her custody battle before the State House. Faucher subsequently became involved in an anti-violence organization called Safe Passage that had formed the Battered Mother's Testimony Project. She served as a board member of Safe Passage for about five and a half years. Faucher is currently happily married to her spouse Andrea Martelli, and has reunited with her children. She is a supporter of President Obama and Senator Warren, and one of her greatest political passions is the movement for gay marriage.
    This interview is available for research without restriction. No online access.
    - Transcript of interview of Dawn M. Faucher (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Anne Foss interviewed by Francie Hiza, 2014 November 9; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    In this oral history Anne Foss describes her childhood in the 1950s and her connection with her parents. She describes noticeable differences between now and then, such as willingness to obey parents. She addresses her own struggles with being a parent contrasted with her fairly smooth transition into having same-sex relationships. She repeats frequently that she "just lives her life" and doesn't worry too much about labels, what other people are saying, or why she chose to be involved with women after her marriage broke up. Foss believes who you love or have relationships with is less important than being a good, kind person.
    Anne Foss (b.1945) grew up in Chappaqua, New York and was raised as an only child after her two older brothers moved out when she was seven. Her family was upper-middle class and was involved in the textile industry. She was very athletic growing up but there were no athletic opportunities at Connecticut College, where she completed her undergraduate degree. She went on to Harvard for a master's program and found jobs easy to come by. Foss married Peter Feig and had her two children with him: Jenny and Michael Foss-Feig. When she divorced him she became involved with a woman, this was the first serious same-sex relationship of her life. Foss met Bobbie Emery a year after separating from the first woman and has been with Emery ever since. They have been married since 2013 and together they run East-West Builders and maintain a farm at Hillstead Museum in Farmington, Connecticut.
    - Transcript of interview of Elizabeth Anne Foss (Box 1)
  - Joyce Gold interviewed by Annie Berman, 2014 October 31; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    Joyce Gold (b. 1944) grew up in Hazelton, Pennsylvania, and moved Queens, New York for high school and college. She graduated from Queens College with a degree in English, and later earned an MA in Metropolitan Studies. Gold's employment history includes teaching English in high school, working as systems analyst for fourteen years, and a real estate broker for four years. Since 1976, she has run her own business, designing, leading, and arranging walking history tours of New York City neighborhoods. Since 1980 she has also been an adjunct assistant professor at NYU and the New School, teaching classes in Manhattan history. In the seventies, she was active in the women's and lesbian movements, serving as treasurer of New York's National Organization of Women (NOW). She met her current wife in 1993. They married in 2003 in Toronto. Gold lives with her wife in New York City.
    - Transcript of interview of Joyce Gold (Box 1)
  - Barbara Herbert interviewed by Carmen Pullella, 2014 October 25; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    In this oral history Barbara Herbert describes the many experiences in her life and the way in which they shaped her into who she is today. As a prominent figure in the medical field, Barbara is very involved in the medical community in and around Boston. Her interest in public health and medicine emerged from the rage she felt in regard to the way in which women were being treated at the time. Barbara was a fervent activist and was involved in many of the big movements in LGBT history, although she makes it clear that she was not a "professional lesbian", and that her activism was very much rooted in a personal and simplistic way of living. She talks about the efforts she and her friends and partners made towards liberation, and towards changing the world in which they lived. Now an expert in emergency medicine and a well-known activist, mother, and intellectual, Barbara lives in Cambridge, MA with her partner Jean.
    Barbara Herbert was born in Baltimore, MD in 1948. Throughout her life, she lived in South Carolina, New York City, and Boston, where she now lives with her partner Jean McGuire, who she met in 1990 and married in 2004. Before meeting Jean, Barbara was in a one-year heterosexual marriage with Robert Herbert in 1968. She had many girlfriends after that, and a great love, Margot, who passed away in 1974. Besides Jean, Barbara's family includes her three children Elena Polikoff (31), Daniel McGuire (34) and Megan McGuire (36). Barbara attended Wellesley College on a fellowship, and then Stonybrook University of New York for graduate school, from where she received her MD. She now specializes in Addiction and Emergency Medicine, and is the Medical Director at St. Elizabeth's Medical Center in Brighton, MA. She is affiliated with the American Public Health Association and the Massachusetts Medical Society, and is involved with many political and professional organizations. Her medical expertise has influenced her activist and political work in the field of human rights, global health and AIDS. Barbara is also an avid activist in the field of anti-poverty, gay liberation, anti-violence, anti-racist and disability rights.
    - Transcript of interview of Barbara Herbert (Box 1)
  - Clare Higgins interviewed by Tegan Waring, 2014 November 16; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    In this oral history Clare Higgins describes her childhood in a large family of six in Brooklyn, New York and associated experiences of being a youth in the turbulent and charged political and social justice era of the 1960's. The interview specifically focuses on her tenure as mayor of the City of Northampton and her experience in other local government positions. Higgins's illustrates her passion and related political activism to housing, early childhood education, and associated problems with the working class. Higgin's story details the changing culture and demographics of Northampton, life as a lesbian in political and public spheres, and the plights of women politicians today.
    Clare Higgins was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 1955 to a college professor and a stay at home mother whom later became a librarian. She grew up in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and Brooklyn, New York with her six siblings but has lived in Northampton, Massachusetts since 1977. Higgins formally attended Brooklyn College and Greenfield Community College then officially received her degree from the University of Massachusetts program, University Without Walls, in 2003.
    Higgins has been an avid civil servant since locating to Northampton, MA. She has been on numerous committees, boards, and commissions; chairing and presiding over many. These include, but are not excluded to, Massachusetts Association for Education and Care, Northampton Housing Authority, Northampton Community Partnerships for Children Advisory Council, and Governor's Advisory Commission on Local Government. However, she is most known for her tenure as Mayor of Northampton (six terms: January 2000-September 2011). Currently, Higgins is the executive director at Community Action of the Franklin, Hampshire and North Quabbin Regions.
    Closed until 2029 January 1
    - Transcript of interview of Clare Higgins (Box 3)
  - Amy MacKenzie interviewed by Emily Coffin, 2014 October 26; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    Amy MacKenzie was born just outside Exeter, NH in 1956 but has spent most of the past 35 years in the Pioneer Valley. During the late 70's she was "living the hippy-ish flannel lifestyle of the baby dyke" and stayed here until she started a family. She has a daughter, Liza, who was among the first of the lesbian baby boom of the 1980's. Her family was featured on TV and in the book Love Makes a Family. She currently works as a school bus driver but was previously a vocational coordinator for people with developmental disabilities and was the first woman garbage collector in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts.
    - Transcript of interview of Amy MacKenzie (Box 1)
  - Anne L. Moore interviewed by Stefana Breiwieser, 2014 November 6; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    In this oral history, Anne Moore examines her life through the lens of her sexuality. Beginning with her childhood, she describes her time on her family's farm and her first experiences confronting sexuality and gender. She then discusses her time in college, her introduction to librarianship, and her involvement within intersecting lesbian and sports communities. Moore goes on to discuss her move to the United States, where she advanced her career, participated in feminist and LGBT activism, and encountered the difficulties of being out in the Midwest. The latter half of the interview focuses on her activism as the chair of the American Library Association's GLBT Round Table, her work documenting the lives of early female faculty members at the University of Massachusetts Amherst, and the importance of preserving of gay and lesbian history. She also discusses her experiences surrounding the 2013 Supreme Court repeal of the Defense of Marriage Act, her thoughts on married life, and how they affect her immigrant status.
    Anne Moore (b. 1956) grew up in rural London, Ontario and lived in Southern Ontario for much of her young adult life. She earned her Masters in History from the University of Guelph and her Masters in Library Science from the University of Western Ontario (now Western University). In the mid-1990s, she immigrated to the United States, living in Nebraska and Oklahoma before finally settling down in Western Massachusetts, where she is working towards U.S. citizenship. Today she works as an archivist at the University of Massachusetts Amherst and is a chair at the GLBT Roundtable of the American Library Association. She is also involved with a number of local community organizations, including the Valley Women's History Collaborative, the Rural Women's Studies Association, the Agricultural History Society, and the UMass Labor Management Workplace Education Program. She currently lives in South Hadley, MA with her spouse, Vivian Ostrowski, and their two dogs.
    - Transcript of interview of Anne L. Moore (Box 1)
  - Mary Clare Powell interviewed by Kaitlin Clark Hackbarth, 2014 November 14; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    In this oral history, seventy-two-year-old poet Mary Clare Powell reflects on her self-proclaimed identity as an atypical woman. Powell describes her upbringing, focusing in particular on the role of community in her hometown of Greenbelt, Maryland, and the role of the community's liberal Protestant church during her youth. She discusses how women throughout her life have helped her in realizing her full potential. Powell talks about coming to terms with her lesbian identity, and how various relationships helped her in doing so. She talks about the traveling she has done throughout her life. She considers the conscious practice of family building, what shaped the way she built her family, and the lessons she has learned in the process of building a non-traditional family. She also discusses her current relationship with religion, as well as her identity as a Christian person practicing Buddhism. The oral history ends with a reading of her poem "Old Love" from her first published book of poetry Things Owls Ate (2001 Amherst Writers and Artists Press). Powell's reflections on her story detail a richly complex and multi-faceted life.
    Mary Clare Powell (b. 1942) is a lesbian-identified retired adjunct professor at Lesley University and a poet currently residing in Greenfield, Massachusetts. Powell was born in Washington, D.C. on March 28, 1942. She was raised in a cooperative community located in Greenbelt, Maryland. She is the only female child in her family, and the eldest of three children. The liberal Protestant church in the Greenbelt community was of great importance to Powell during her formative years. Religion continued to play an important role in Powell's life throughout her adolescences and adulthood. Powell's desire to be an educator from a young age drove her to earn her B.S. in Education and English from Towson State College (now Towson University), her M.L.A. in the History of Ideas from Johns Hopkins University, and her Ed.D in Creativity and Education from the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. Powell has taught English, poetry, and photography inside and outside of the formal classroom setting. Powell is particularly interested in poetry and photography, and these interests (combined with her role as an educator) have allowed her to travel extensively. Powell participated in various activist movements, the anti-Vietnam war movement, the Civil Rights movement, and the feminist and gay and lesbian movements. She has lived in western Massachusetts since 1984. Around this time, Powell met her spouse, Violet Walker, and Walker's two daughters. Since then, Powell's family has grown to include two grandchildren, a godson, and her brother's children and grandchildren. She currently writes poetry and gives regular readings of her poetry with musical accompaniment from her partner. She meets with fellow writers and helps them during the editing and publishing processes. She also practices Buddhism, and leads group meditation practices and Centering Prayer Buddhist sangha weekly.
    - Transcript of interview of Mary Clare Powell (Box 2)
  - Lesley Schneider interviewed by Isabella Levy, 2014 October 30; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    Closed until 2025 January 1
    - Transcript of interview of Lesley Schneider (Box 3)
  - Jane Stangl interviewed by Martha Middleton Biddle, 2014 November 15; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    Closed until "official resignation from Smith College is rendered" or 50 years after the oral history's submission. No online access.
    - Transcript of interview of Jane Stangl (Box 3)
  - LW (pseudonym) interviewed by Samantha Weiss, 2014 October 21; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    Closed until 2034 January 1; narrator is to be identified by pseudonym, L.W. No online access.
    - Transcript of interview of LW (Box 3)
  - Marianne Winters interviewed by Megan Bowles, 2014 November 19; 1 oral histories (transcript)
    In this oral history Marianne Winters describes her childhood growing up in a working-class, conservative Catholic family in the Syracuse region of New York. Her story details her leadership and activism in college, her own experience with traumatic violence, and her coming out process in young adulthood. The interview focuses on her work against sexual assault during the early stages of the anti-violence movement at a rape crisis center in Worcester, MA. One of her major contributions to the movement was fighting for survivor confidentiality in legal cases. The interview also involves her experience with the sex wars, AIDS, and the conservative political climate in the 1980s.Winters discusses the marriage equality movement and family life raising two children with her partner. Her oral history involves her work at Safe Passage in Northampton, thoughts on current activism around sexual assault and domestic violence, and next steps for the anti-violence movement.
    Marianne Winters (b. 1960) grew up in the Syracuse region, graduated from the College of Saint Rose in 1982, and went on to earn an M.S. in Education from Southern Illinois University at Carbondale. Winters has been a leader in the anti-violence movement for the past three decades. Over the course of her career, she has worked for social change and an end to sexualized and domestic violence in many capacities. She has held leadership positions at the Rape Crisis Center of Central Massachusetts, the Massachusetts Coalition Against Sexual Assault, Jane Doe Inc., the Everywoman's Center at UMass Amherst, and Praxis for Change. She also serves as a member of the Governor's Council to Address Sexual Assault and Domestic Violence. She has been a leader in expanding outreach to underserved communities, including lesbian victims of violence. Throughout her career, she has expanded discourse and action around violence and abuse within LGBTQ communities. Currently, she serves as Executive Director at Safe Passage, a domestic violence agency in Northampton.
    - Transcript of interview of Marianne Winters (Box 2)
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2016, 2,150.4 Gigabytes (86 digital video and text files)
  - Brenda J. Ahl interviewed by Sydney Ramirez, 2016 March 12; 1 oral histories
    Brenda Ahl (b. 1964) grew up in upstate New York and southern California. Ahl was on active duty in the U.S. Army from 1984-1988 in Savannah, GA and served in the Army Reserve as a U.S. Military police officer thereafter, totaling 22 years of service. Ahl is a Gulf War veteran and has been engaged as a federal law enforcement officer in a variety of capacities, including as an instructor at Military Intel Interrogation School and as a Spanish language instructor. She was in a heterosexual marriage for 5 years and became comfortable identifying as gay after her divorce. She was in a relationship for 8 years before her partner Dawn passed away. Ahl has two children and currently lives with her wife of 11 years.
    In this oral history Brenda Ahl describes her childhood and adolescence in Southern California. The interview covers her career and experience as a woman in male-dominated fields, coming to terms with and reconciling her gay identity and Christian faith, and her experience as a single gay mother in the 1990s and the challenges of step-parenthood. Ahl reflects on lesbian and gay life in the military in the early 80s, gay and lesbian nightlife in Savannah, GA and northern California, and the role of sexuality in law enforcement. The interview also addresses issues of race and LGBT rights in the current social context.
    - Transcript of interview of Brenda J. Ahl (Box 1)
  - Beth Caurant interviewed by Becca Damante, 2016 April 1; 1 oral histories
    Beth Caurant (b. 1952) founded one of the first all-women's rock and lesbian bands, Lilith, in 1972. Caurant grew up in Lenox, MA with her mother and her older sister, and moved to Granby when her mother got remarried. After high school, Caurant studied at Holyoke Community College and the University of Massachusetts, where she pursued an English major and Women's Studies minor. She left the University in 1977 in order to pursue her music career with Lilith, which lasted from 1972 to 1978 and resulted in one album called Boston Ride as well as many successful performances in Massachusetts and Georgia. In 1994, she moved to Northampton with her partner of 23 years. Today, she is retired and plays music locally.
    In this oral history, Beth Caurant describes her childhood in a working-class family in Western Massachusetts, and her early relationships with girls and women in the 1960s and 1970s. Her interview focuses on the successes and struggles she faced as the founder and guitarist in the band Lilith. Throughout the interview, Caurant reflects on the lesbian community in Northampton, her identification as a natural feminist, and her thoughts on current LGBT and feminist politics such as transgender issues, same-sex marriage, and women in the music industry.